<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Release Notes</title>
    <author email="brad at archive dot org">Brad Tofel</author>
    <revision>$Id: index.xml 2040 2007-10-12 23:21:40Z bradtofel $</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Releases">
      <p>
        Full listing of changes and bug fixes are not currently available prior
        to release 1.2.0.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Release 1.2.0">
      <subsection name="Features">
        <ul>
          <li>
            now supports compressed and uncompressed ARC and WARC files.
          </li>
          <li>
            initial revision of "deduplicated" WARC record handling, which
            returns the last version that was actually stored when 
            subsequent captures are not saved because they have not changed.
          </li>
          <li>
            now filters (literal) duplicate records from the ResourceIndex,
            in case the same capture (url + date) appears twice, or in two
            CDX files.
          </li>
          <li>
            UrlCanonicalizer is now pluggable, current functionality is now
            implemented in AggressiveUrlCanonicalizer. Added
            IdentityUrlCanonicalizer, which performs no canonicalization.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>bin-search</b> command line tool now outputs a single stream of 
            sorted results from multiple files, instead of returning matches
            from each file sequentially.
          </li>
          <li>
            extracted several replay features into separate jspInserts that
            can now be mixed and matched.
          </li>
          <li>
            now handles most text/css URL rewriting, both inside HTML pages,
            and in externally linked .css files.
          </li>
          <li>
            externalized comment embedded inside replayed HTML pages into
            jspInsert: ArchiveComment.jsp.
          </li>
          <li>
            non-javascript Archival URL replay mode, where all URL rewriting
            occurs on the server. This includes a non-javascript 
            Timeline jspInsert.
          </li>
          <li>
            added two-month timeline partition.
          </li>
          <li>
            root page of webapp now lists access points, when users make
            a request that does not specify one. Also, now access point
            "slash-pages" are available "without the slash".
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Bug Fixes">
        <ul>
          <li>
            Now rewrite Location and Content-Base HTTP headers in non-HTML
            Archival URL replayed documents.
          </li>
          <li>
            now rewrites all <b>background</b> attributes found in returned
            pages (archival URL mode only) instead of just on BODY tags.
          </li>
          <li>
            now rewrites <b>src</b> attributes on INPUT tags.
          </li>
          <li>
            command line tools now allow whitespace arguments, important for
            tools accepting delimiter arguments.
          </li>
          <li>
            replay URLs in query results now include non-standard ports, if
            needed.
          </li>
          <li>
            Timezone is now explicitly set to GMT/UTC, fixing a Calendar
            result partitioning problem.
          </li>
          <li>
            uncaught character-encoding exceptions now handled, plus 
            slightly improved detection of correct character encoding by
            removing internal whitespace in declared encoding names.
          </li>
          <li>
            archival URL parsing of query end-date now assumes latest
            possible date given a partial end-date, instead of earliest
            possible date.
          </li>
          <li>
            re-implemented lost "closest" indicator for XML results.
          </li>
          <li>
            now supports multiple auto index threads, one per ResourceStore,
            and also multiple auto index merge threads, one per BDB 
            ResourceIndex. 
          </li>
          <li>
            fixed hard-coded maximum year issue.
          </li>
          <li>
            reimplemented NotInArchive logging, which was lost in 1.0.0.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>