	
    <filter>
        <filter-name>RemoteSubmitFilter</filter-name>
        <filter-class>org.archive.wayback.resourceindex.indexer.RemoteSubmitFilter</filter-class>
        <init-param>
            <param-name>pipeline.statusjsp</param-name>
            <param-value>jsp/PipelineUI/PipelineStatus.jsp</param-value>
        </init-param>
    </filter>
    <filter-mapping>
        <filter-name>RemoteSubmitFilter</filter-name>
        <url-pattern>/index-incoming/*</url-pattern>
    </filter-mapping>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourceindex.classname</param-name>
        <param-value>org.archive.wayback.resourceindex.LocalResourceIndex</param-value>
        <description>Class that implements ResourceIndex for this Wayback</description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourceindex.sourceclass</param-name>
        <param-value>BDB</param-value>
        <description>Class that implements ResultSource for this Wayback, 
        currently: BDB|CDX</description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourceindex.indexpath</param-name>
        <param-value>/tmp/wayback/index</param-value>
        <description>
            LocalBDBResourceIndex specific directory to store the BDB files.
            Directory must exists.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourceindex.dbname</param-name>
        <param-value>DB1</param-value>
        <description>
            LocalBDBResourceIndex specific name for BDB database
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourceindex.incomingpath</param-name>
        <param-value>/tmp/wayback/index-data/incoming</param-value>
        <description>
            BDB index-specific configuration that indicates new CDX format flat
            files will appear in the directory named in the value of this param.
            If this configuration is present and non-empty, a background thread
            will be started that monitors this directory, and adds CDX records
            in files found in this directory to the index.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourceindex.mergedpath</param-name>
        <param-value>/tmp/wayback/index-data/merged</param-value>
        <description>
            If this value is present and non-empty, then CDX files that are
            successfully processed from incoming are moved to this directory
            after merging. If this option is missing or blank, CDX files are
            deleted after merging.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourceindex.failedpath</param-name>
        <param-value>/tmp/wayback/index-data/failed</param-value>
        <description>
            If this value is present and non-empty, then CDX files that fail to
            parse successfully are moved to this directory after a single 
            attempt. If this option is missing or blank, malformed CDX files are
            left in the incoming directory and repeatedly re-attempted until
            some other process moves them out of the way or fixes them.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourceindex.mergeinterval</param-name>
        <param-value>10000</param-value>
        <description>
            Millisecond interval between checks for new files in the incoming 
            directory. This is only the starting number, when no new files are
            found in the directory. Each subsequent interval will increase by 
            this number of ms, until a file is found, at which point the 
            interval will revert to the initial level.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>maxresults</param-name>
        <param-value>1000</param-value>
        <description>
        	Maximum number of results to return from the ResourceIndex.
        </description>
    </context-param>

