	
    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourcestore.classname</param-name>
        <param-value>org.archive.wayback.resourcestore.LocalARCResourceStore</param-value>
        <description>Class that implements ResourceStore for this Wayback</description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourcestore.arcpath</param-name>
        <param-value>/tmp/wayback/arcs</param-value>
        <description>
            Directory where ARC files are found (possibly where Heritrix writes them.)
            This directory must exist.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourcestore.autoindex</param-name>
        <param-value>1</param-value>
        <description>
            If this is set to '1', then a background thread is launched that
            detects new ARC files appearing in arcpath. New ARCs are indexed,
            and a CDX flat file, with one line per ARC Record is created, one
            CDX file per ARC. These CDX files are then handed off to the index
            for incorporation into the index.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourcestore.tmppath</param-name>
        <param-value>/tmp/wayback/arc-indexer/tmp</param-value>
        <description>
            Directory where CDX files are created temporarily. This is a 
            scratch space directory, which must exist.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourcestore.workpath</param-name>
        <param-value>/tmp/wayback/arc-indexer/work</param-value>
        <description>
            Directory which holds empty flag files indicating that ARC files 
            are waiting to be indexed.
            This directory must exist.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourcestore.queuedpath</param-name>
        <param-value>/tmp/wayback/arc-indexer/queued</param-value>
        <description>
            Directory which holds empty flag files indicating that ARC files 
            have already been seen and queued for indexing.
            This directory must exist.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourcestore.indextarget</param-name>
        <param-value>/tmp/wayback/index-data/incoming</param-value>
        <description>
            Directory or URL where CDX files are sent after they are created. If
            the value of this parameter begins with http://, then the value is
            assumed to be a URL where CDX files are PUT, on a possibly remote
            resourceindex node. If the value does not begin with http://, then
            the value is assumed to be a local directory, which must exist, 
            where completed CDX files are moved for incorporation into the 
            index.
        </description>
    </context-param>

    <context-param>
        <param-name>resourcestore.indexinterval</param-name>
        <param-value>10000</param-value>
        <description>
            Millisecond interval between checks for new ARCs that need to be 
            processed. This is only the initial time slept when first starting
            up, and after any new files are found. Each interval that no new 
            ARCs are detected, the duration slept increases by this amount.
        </description>
    </context-param>

