<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Release Hisotry</title>
    <author email="brad at archive dot org">Brad Tofel</author>
    <author email="helen hockx-yu at bl dot uk">Helen Hockx-Yu</author>
    <revision>$ID:12-09-2014$</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>
        <p><b>OpenWayback is supported the International Internet Preservation Consortium (IIPC) and the member institutions with which the contributors of the project are affiliated.</b>
        </p>
    <section name="Releases">
        <subsection name="OpenWayback 2.0.0 Release - 12th September 2014">
          <p>
          OpenWayback 2.0.0 release is a culmination of the two previous beta releases. It includes bug fixes and significant improvement of documentation. Existing documentation has been identified, reorganised and updated. A set of essential documentation is included in the release.<br></br>
            Please see <a href="release_notes.html">release notes</a> for a detailed list of changes. 
          </p>
          <p><a href="https://github.com/iipc/openwayback/tree/openwayback-2.0.0">https://github.com/iipc/openwayback/tree/openwayback-2.0.0</a>  
         </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="OpenWayback 2.0.0 BETA 2 Release - 14th May 2014">
          <p>
            OpenWayback 2.0.0 BETA 2 release includes bug fixes and a number of enhancements, including better support for WARCs and integration of JWAT ResourceStore. A consistent naming scheme has been applied to the artifactId, the github project name, and the jar name. In addition, documentation has been improved, manual testing experience documented and a sample overlay provided, allowing easier customisations of the standard wayback-webapp.
            <br></br>
            Please see <a href="release_notes.html">release notes</a> for a detailed list of changes. 
           </p>
          <p><a href="https://github.com/iipc/openwayback/tree/openwayback-2.0.0.BETA.2">https://github.com/iipc/openwayback/tree/openwayback-2.0.0.BETA.2</a>  
          </p>
        </subsection>
        
        
        <subsection name="OpenWayback 2.0.0.BETA 1 Release - 10th January 2014">
          <p>
            OpenWayback 2.0.0 BETA 1 release mainly reflects the move of ownership of the lead repository from the Internet Archive to the IIPC. This includes a set of changes to the IA codebase to make it more independent of their build server and some non-public artefacts. Moreover, it includes updates from the internetarchive/wayback fork, corresponding to the move of critical code from internetarchive/heritrix3 to iipc/iipc-web-commons. <br></br>
            Please see <a href="release_notes.html">release notes</a> for a detailed list of changes. 
          </p>
          <p><a href="https://github.com/iipc/openwayback/tree/openwayback-2.0.0.BETA.1">https://github.com/iipc/openwayback/tree/openwayback-2.0.0.BETA.1</a>
          </p>
<p><b>The following releases of the Open Source Wayback Machine (OSWM) were made by the Internet Archive, who led its development since 2005. The on-going development of Wayback was handed over to the International Internet Preservation Consortium (IIPC) in October 2013, when the OpenWayback project was launched. For more details please see <a href="https://github.com/iipc/openwayback/wiki/General-Overview">General Overview</a></b>
	
</p>          
          
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="New Release - 1.8.0, 18/12/2013">
        <p>Release notes not available. Among other features, the <a href="https://github.com/iipc/openwayback/tree/master/wayback-cdx-server">wayback-cdx-server</a> was introduced, which is a standalone HTTP servlet that serves the index that the wayback machine uses to lookup captures.
        	</p>
        </subsection> 
        <subsection name="New Release - 1.7.0, 09/02/2013">
        <p>Release notes not available.</p>
        	
        </subsection>
        New Release – 1.8.0, 18/12/2013



New Release – 1.7.0, 09/02/2013


        <subsection name="New Release - 1.6.0, 1/3/2011">
          <p>
            The 1.6.0 release is now available, with improved
            server-side rewriting of HTML, CSS, Javascript, and SWF content.
            This version includes other new features and bug fixes, which are
            detailed on the <a href="release_notes.html">release notes</a> page.
            Upgrading to this version will require changes to Wayback Spring XML
            configuration.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Maintenance Release - 1.4.2, 7/17/2009">
          <p>
            Release 1.4.2 fixes several problems discovered in the 1.4.1 
            release. Please see the <a href="release_notes.html">release notes</a> for
            a detailed list of changes.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Maintenance Release - 1.4.1, 11/10/2008">
          <p>
            Release 1.4.1 fixes several problems discovered in the 1.4.0 
            release, and most notably disables by default the AnchorDate and
            AnchorWindow features which generated some confusion. Please
            see the <a href="release_notes.html">release notes</a> for
            a detailed list of changes.
          </p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="New Release - 1.4.0, 8/20/2008">
          <p>
            Release 1.4.0 has several new features, as well as several 
            bug-fixes. This version includes substantial code changes and
            refactoring to consolidate and expand current functionality as well
            as enable several future planned features. Notable new features
            include the ability to insert content in replayed HTML pages within
            Proxy and DomainPrefix replay modes, the ability to scan multiple
            local directories recursively for ARC/WARC files, and a feature
            within Archival URL replay mode to prevent time drift during a
            replay session.
          </p>
          <p>
            Please see the <a href="release_notes.html">Release Notes</a> for
            specific features and bug fixes.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="New Release - 1.2.0, 1/30/2008">
          <p>
            Release 1.2.0 has several new features, as well as several 
            bug-fixes. Wayback now supports compressed and uncompressed 
            ARC and WARC formats. Previously there was only support for 
            compressed ARC files. This version also includes a new Archival URL
            replay mechanism, where all URL rewriting occurs on the server,
            obviating the need for client-side Javascript, and preventing
            some request leakage. This version also includes the capability to
            replace the default URL canonicalization scheme(currently there is
            still only one implementation available, but the groundwork for
            using different schemes is now in place.) This version also
            includes support for de-duplicated WARC records. 
          </p>
          <p>
            Please see the <a href="release_notes.html">Release Notes</a> for
            specific features and bug fixes.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="New Release - 1.0.0, 10/12/2007">
          <p>
            Release 1.0.0 has several significant changes, most notably a
            completely new configuration mechanism using Spring IOC. This new
            configuration system introduces some deployment concepts:
            <ul>
              <li>
                <b>WaybackCollections</b> define a set of documents via the
                previously existing ResourceStore and ResourceIndex 
                implementations.
              </li>
              <li>
                <b>AccessPoints</b> define a method by which users can access
                and interact with a WaybackCollection. A single 
                WaybackCollection may be exposed to users through several
                AccessPoints simultaneously. Each AccessPoint specifies an
                access URL, a Query interface, a Replay interface, and
                several optional access restrictions, including limiting who
                can connect to the AccessPoint, and which documents in the 
                WaybackCollection are available through the AccessPoint.   
              </li>
            </ul>
            This new configuration frameworks allows hosting of hundreds of
            individual collections within a single wayback installation, each
            with potentially multiple AccessPoints.
          </p>
          <p>
            This version also includes a major refactoring of the Replay User
            Interface framework, simplifying extension and the creation of novel
            replay modes. Specifically, one or more external .jsp files can 
            be used to generate additional HTML content within replayed HTML 
            pages. The Timeline Replay mode has been completely replaced by one
            of these external .jsp files, which inserts the Timeline banner 
            inside replayed HTML pages.
          </p>
          <p>
            This version includes a very experimental new Replay mode, 
            <i>domain-prefix</i> replay mode, which performs all markup and
            recontextualization of replayed HTML documents on the server-side,
            eliminating the need for client-side Javascript execution. Please
            ask on the discussion list for assistance in using this Replay mode.
          </p>
          <p>
            Lastly, this version has some internal improvements which should 
            reduce memory consumption, and the software is now built using 
            maven2.  
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="New Release - 0.8.0, 01/11/2007">
            <p>
            	Release 0.8.0 offers several new features, most notably a CDX
            	format flat file ResourceIndex implementation, improved 
            	character set detection, and many smaller improvements, 
            	bug-fixes, and optimizations.
            	<ul>
            		<b>Major Features:</b>
					<li>
						Added Sorted CDX flat file ResourceIndex implementation,
						allowing for much larger data sets.
					</li>
					<li>
						Improved character set detection so pages are not
						mangled when server side modification occurs.
					</li>
					<li>
						Several new command-line tools, for generating and
						updating each ResourceIndex type.
					</li>
					<li>
						Bug-fixes to allow integration with NutchWax full-text
						searching.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="New Release - 0.6.0, 07/14/2006">
            <p>
            	Release 0.6.0 offers:
	            <ul>
	            	<li>
	            		Timeline Mode - comparable with WERA user interface.
	            	</li>
	            	<li>
						Manual Exclusions - allows for blocking sites and paths
						from the index for specific ranges of time.
	            	</li>
	            </ul>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="New Release - 0.4.0, 03/28/2006">
            <p>
            	Release 0.4.0 offers many new features and improvements, 
            	including:
	            <ul>
	            	<li>
	            		Distributed ARC storage.
	            	</li>
	            	<li>
	            		Improved Javascript and document rewriting for Archival
	            		URL replay mode.
	            	</li>
	            	<li>
	            		Several new ResourceIndex implementations: Remote BDB, 
	            		NutchWax.
	            	</li>
	            	<li>
	            		live web robots.txt caching and retroactive compliance.
	            	</li>
	            	<li>
	            		"Classic" Wayback Machine query User Interface.
	            	</li>
	            </ul>
            </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="First Release - 0.2.0, 12/09/2005">
            <p>
            First public release of the open source wayback.
            </p>
        </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
