<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Home Page</title>
    <author email="brad at archive dot org">Brad Tofel</author>
    <revision>$Id$</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Introduction">
        <p><b>wayback</b> is an open source java implementation of the
        The Internet Archive Wayback Machine.
        </p>
        <p>
        The current production version of the Wayback Machine is implemented in
        perl, and lacks in maintainability and extensibility. Also, the code is
        not open source. Primary motivation for the new version is to address 
        these three issues, enabling public distribution of the application, and
        easy experimentation with new features and access technologies.
        </p>
        <p>
        The current Java version of the Wayback Machine supports two access, or
        replay modes of operation: "Archival Url" mode and "Proxy" mode.
        </p>
        <p>
        Archival URL mode provides a user experience very close to the current
        production Wayback Machine. All query and replay access requests can be 
        expressed as URLs. In Archival Url replay mode, HTML documents are 
        delivered with additional Javascript embedded in the page. This 
        Javascript alters the document within the browser, attempting to make 
        links and embedded content refer back to the Wayback Machine by 
        rewriting them as Archival URLs.
        </p>
        <p>
        Proxy URL mode allows replaying of archived documents within a client
        browser by configuring the browser to proxy all HTTP requests through
        the Wayback Machine. This has the strong advantage that no Javascript 
        page markup is required to coerce the client browser to request 
        additional URLs and embedded content from the Wayback Machine -- content
        just works as-is. One major disadvantage of this mode is that there is
        no way to forward temporal information with each replay request. Because
        of this limitation, only the most recently archived version of any 
        resource is accessible thru the Wayback Machine in proxy Url mode. 
        Another limitation of the Proxy URL mode is that it requires special
        configuration of the client web browser to access the Wayback Service. 
        This browser configuration is not complex, but it means that content 
        cannot be accessed as a global URL.
        </p>
        <p>
        The current Java version is intended to operate as a standalone webapp,
        maintaining an index on the machine hosting the webapp. This index
        contains records of the resources within a set of ARC files, which are
        also assumed to be stored on the same machine hosting the webapp.
        </p>
        <p>
        This software includes the capability to scan for ARC files in a 
        specified location, and to automatically index and serve content in
        newly discovered ARC files as they appear. Directing the Wayback 
        Machine to look for ARC files in the directory where an instance of the
        Heritrix web crawler is writing ARC output should provide the 
        capability to browse content archived by Heritrix as it is crawled.
        </p>
        <p>
        Future versions of this software may integrate more tightly with the 
        Heritrix web crawler application.
        </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
